<chapter id="chapter-sesame-intro">
	<title>Short introduction to Sesame's components</title>
	<para>
		Before diving into the internals of Sesame, we will start with a short
		introduction to Sesame, giving a high-level overview of its components.
		It's important to have some basic knowledge about this as the rest of
		this document will often refer to various components that are touched
		upon here. It is assumed that the reader has at least some basic
		knowledge about RDF, RDF Schema, OWL, etc. If this is not the case, some
		introductory articles can be found at the following locations:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem><ulink url="http://www.rdfabout.net/"/></listitem>
		<listitem><emphasis>TODO: add more semweb intro URLs</emphasis></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		We will try to explain the Sesame framework using the following figure,
		which shows the main components and APIs in Sesame and how they are
		built on top of each other. Each component/API depends on the
		components/APIs that are directly beneath them.
	</para>
	<figure id="figure-sesame-components" float="1">
		<title>A high-level overview of Sesame's components and their dependencies</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/sesame-components.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para> 
		All the way at the bottom of the diagram is the RDF Model, the fundament
		of the Sesame framework. Being an RDF-oriented framework, all parts of
		Sesame are to some extent dependent on this RDF model, which defines
		interfaces and implementation for all basic RDF entities: URI, blank
		node, literal and statement.
	</para>
	<para>
		Rio, which stands for "RDF I/O", consists of a set of parsers and
		writers for various RDF file formats. The parsers can be used to
		translate RDF files to lists of statements, and the writers for the
		reverse operation. Rio can also be used independent of the rest of
		Sesame and is distributed separately for this purpose.
	</para>
	<para> 
		The Storage And Inference Layer (Sail) API is a low level System API
		(SPI) for RDF stores and inferencers. Its purpose is to abstract from
		the storage and inference details, allowing various types of storage and
		inference to be used. The Sail API is mainly of interest for those who
		are developing Sail implementation, for all others it suffices to know
		how to create and configure one.
	</para>
	<para> 
		The Repository API is a higer level API that offers a large number of
		developer-oriented methods for handling RDF data. The main goal of this
		API is to make the life of application developers as easy as possible.
		It offers various methods for uploading data files, querying, and
		extracting and manipulating data. It depends on Rio for parsing and
		writing RDF files, and on the Sail API for storage and retrieval of RDF
		data.
	</para>
	<para>
		The top-most component in the diagram is the HTTP Server. The HTTP
		Server consists of a number of Java Servlets that implement a protocol
		for accessing Sesame repositories over HTTP. The details of this
		protocol can be found in Sesame's system documentation, but most people
		can simply use a client library to handle the communication. (Note: the
		client libraries are not yet available for the first alpha release of
		Sesame 2.)
	</para>
	<para>
		While each part of the Sesame code is publicly available and
		extensible, most application developers will be primarily interested
		in the Repository API. This API is described in more detail in the
		next chapter.
	</para>
</chapter>
