<chapter id="chapter-introduction"> 
	<title>Architecture</title>
	<para>
		The following figure shows the main components and APIs in Sesame and
		how they are built on top of each other:
	</para>
	<figure id="figure-sesame-arch" float="1">
		<title>The Sesame architecture</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/block-diagram.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>
	<para>
		Being an RDF-oriented framework, all parts of Sesame are to some extent
		related to the RDF model. This model defines interfaces for the RDF
		entities "URI", "blank node", "literal" and "statement".
	</para>
	<para>
		Sesame has two main communication interfaces: the Sail API and the
		Repository API. The Storage And Inference Layer (Sail) API is a low
		level system API (or: SPI) for RDF stores and inferencers. It's
		purpose is to abstract from the storage details, allowing various types
		of storage and inference to be used.
	</para>
	<para>
		The Repository API is a higer level API and is meant to be the main API
		that people can program against. It offers various methods for uploading
		data files, querying, and extracting and manipulating data. It comes in
		two flavours: local and remote. The local Repository API can be used for
		"local" repositories, as in "running in the same Java Virtual Machine".
		The remote Repository API can be used in client-server settings, where
		the application communicates with a Sesame server. The two flavours
		share a common interface so that applications can be developed to work
		with both local and remote repositories transparently.
	</para>
	<para>
		Part of the Sail API is the Sail Query Model, which can be used to build
		object models representing queries. A query engine like the SeRQL engine
		takes care of parsing query strings and building such query object model
		from them. These query object models can then be passed to Sail objects,
		which take care of their evaluation.
	</para>
	<para>
		Rio stands for "RDF I/O" and consists of a set of parsers and writers
		for various RDF file formats. The parsers can be used to translate RDF
		files to lists of statements, and the writers for the reverse operation.
		Rio is used by the Repository API for data import and export, but can
		also be used directly by applications.
	</para>
</chapter>
