<chapter id="chapter-sailapi" xreflabel="Sail API">
	<title>Sail API</title>

	<figure id="figure-sail-api-uml" float="1">
		<title>Class diagram for the Sail API</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/org_openrdf_sesame_sail.jpg"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>
		The class diagram above shows the main Sail interfaces from package
			<ulink url="../apidocs/org/openrdf/sail/package-summary.html">
			org.openrdf.sesame.sail</ulink>.
		The Sail API defines a set of interfaces for RDF stores and inferencers.
		The main interface is Sail, which defines methods to initialize, query,
		modify and shut down the Sail object.
	</para>
	<para>
		For scalability reasons, all data that is extracted from a Sail object
		is returned in the form of (forward-only) iterators. This allows one to
		fetch the entire set of stored statements, even if the set is to large
		to store in main memory. Queries are expressed in terms of the Sail
		Query Model (see <xref linkend="chapter-sailquerymodel"/>).
	</para>
	<para>
		New in Sesame 2.0 is the concept of statement contexts; a grouping
		mechanism for statements. Statements can now be stored in contexts which
		are identified by a URI or a blank node. Statements that are not stored
		in a specific context are stored in the "default context". The Sail
		interface defines methods for extracting the statements from a specific
		context, from the default context, or from all contexts combined.
	</para>
	<para>
		Also new in Sesame 2.0 is proper transaction support. Transactions are
		modelled as separate objects, which is thought to be the most general
		approach to modelling transactions: it allows the caller to create
		transactions per object, per thread, or even per application.
		Alternatives for matching commits or rollbacks to the appropriate
		transaction are all more specific, e.g.: based on threads or calling
		objects.
	</para>
	<para>
		A Sail implementation may or may not support features like concurrent
		transactions or transaction isolation; this is not defined by the Sail
		API. Sails that do not have isolated transaction may block any query
		calls during transactions; Sails that do not support concurrent
		transactions might do the same for calls to startTransaction(). Sail
		implementations should clearly document their behaviour with respect to
		concurrent access.
	</para>
	<para>
		Some Sails can be stacked on top of other Sails. These Sails should
		implement the StackableSail interface. By stacking a Sail on top of
		another, all calls for the bottom Sail will pass through the Sails that
		are on top of it (see <xref linkend="figure-sail-stack"/>). This feature
		can be used for a whole range of applications: access control,
		pluggable inferencers, hooks to external services, etc. A concrete
		example is a mixed forward-/backward-chaining inferencer, which will
		wrap transactions to do its forward-chaining work upon commit and
		extend queries to do its backward-chaining work.
	</para>

	<figure id="figure-sail-stack" float="1">
		<title>Example Sail stack</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="figures/sail-stack.png"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>
		SailChangedListener's can register themselves with Sail objects in
		order to be notified of any changes in the stored data. Whenever this
		happens, the Sail will generate a SailChangedEvent and pass it to all
		regsitered listeners.
	</para>
</chapter>
