<chapter id="chapter-sesame2-whats-new">
	<title>rdf:about Sesame 2</title>
	<section>
	  <title>Introduction</title>
		<para>
			Sesame is an open source Java framework for storage and querying of
			RDF data. The framework is fully extensible and configurable with
			respect to storage mechanisms, inferencers, RDF file formats, query
			result formats and query languages. Sesame offers a JBDC-like user
			API, streamlined system APIs and a RESTful HTTP interface supporting
			the SPARQL Protocol for RDF.
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, a framework isn't very useful without implementations of
			the various APIs. Out of the box, Sesame supports SPARQL and SeRQL
			querying, a memory-based and a disk-based RDF store and RDF Schema
			inferencers. It also supports most popular RDF file formats and
			query result formats. Various extensions are available or are being
			worked at elsewhere.
		</para>
		<para>
			Originally, Sesame was developed by
			<ulink url="http://www.aduna-software.com/">Aduna</ulink> (then
			known as Aidministrator) as a research prototype for the hugely
			successful EU research project
			<ulink url="http://www.ontoknowledge.org/">On-To-Knowledge</ulink>.
			When this work ended in 2001, Aduna continued the development in
			cooperation with <ulink url="http://www.nlnet.nl/">NLnet Foundation</ulink>,
			developers from <ulink url="">Ontotext</ulink>, and a number of volunteer developers who
			contribute ideas, bug reports and fixes.
		</para>
		<para>
			Sesame is currently developed as a community project, with Aduna as
			the project leader. Community support is available from
			<ulink url="http://www.openrdf.org/">www.openrdf.org</ulink>. Aduna
			also offers commercial support and consultency services, feel free
			to <ulink url="http://www.aduna-software.com/contact/">contact
				us</ulink> for more information.
		  </para>
		</section>
		<section>
		  <title>How this manual is organized</title>
		  <para>
			 This user manual covers most aspects of working with Sesame in a
			 variety of settings. In <xref linkend="chapter-download" />, we
			 explain how and where to obtain Sesame binaries, source code and/or
			 Maven artifacts. <xref linkend="chapter-sesame-intro" /> gives a
			 brief overview of the architecture of the framework, and is a
			 recommend background read for anyone who intends to start using
			 Sesame. <xref linkend="chapter-lib-install" /> explains how to set up
			 your development enviroment and is useful if you intend to write your
			 own (Java) programs using the Sesame libraries.  In
			 <xref linkend="chapter-server-install" /> we explain how to install the Sesame
			 Server and Workbench web applications, and <xref linkend="chapter-console"/> explains the workings of the Sesame command line console, which is a useful tool to quickly create and use a (local) RDF store, but which can also be used as a command line client to connect with a Sesame Server. In <xref linkend="chapter-datadir-config"/> we explain where Sesame Server, Workbench and Console stores their data and how you can reconfigure that location.
		  </para> 
		  <para>
			 The basics of programming with Sesame are covered in <xref linkend="chapter-repository-api"/>. <xref linkend="chapter-http-protocol"/> gives an overview of the structure of the HTTP REST protocol for the Sesame Server, which is useful if you want to communicate with a Sesame Server from a programming language other than Java. Finally, <xref linkend="chapter-serql"/> documents Sesame's SeRQL query language.
		  </para>
		</section>
</chapter>
