<chapter id="chapter-download">
	<title>Source code and binaries</title>
	<para>
		If you follow the download links from the
		<ulink url="http://www.openrdf.org/download.jsp">download section</ulink>
		at openRDF.org you'll find that there are a number of different files that
		you can download. Which one you need depends on what you want to do with it:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<filename>openrdf-sesame-(version)-sdk.tar.gz</filename>.
			This is a GNU-zipped tar archive of the complete binary version of
			the Sesame SDK. It includes all the Sesame libraries packaged as
			jar files and a set of Web Archive (.war) files for easy
			deployment of Sesame's Web applications (see <xref
				linkend="chapter-server-install"/>). It also includes
			documentation (such as  this user manual, and the API JavaDoc).
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<filename>openrdf-sesame-(version)-sdk.zip</filename>.
			This is a zip archive that has the same contents as the tar.gz
			file mentioned before.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<filename>openrdf-sesame-(version)-onejar.jar</filename>.
			This is a Java Archive (.jar) file containing all the relevant
			Sesame libraries. The main purpose of this jar file is easy
			inclusion of all Sesame components when using it as an embedded
			component/library in your own application: you only need to add
			this one jar file to your classpath and you can start programming
			against it.
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		Apart from these binary downloads,
		<ulink url="http://www.aduna-software.com/">Aduna</ulink> also offers the
		Sesame libraries as maven artifacts in a <emphasis>maven
				repository</emphasis>. This maven repository is located at
		<ulink url="http://repository.aduna-software.org/maven2/"/>.
		Developers using maven can use this repository to automatically
		resolve library dependencies and to get the latest released versions
		of each library. For instructions how to use the maven build system, see
		<ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/"/>.
	</para>
	<para>
		Sesame's source code is available from Aduna's Subversion (SVN) repository:
		<ulink url="https://src.aduna-software.org/svn/org.openrdf/"/>.
		There is an SVN Web Viewer available as well at
		<ulink url="http://src.aduna-software.org/viewvc/org.openrdf/"/>.
		Source code for each release is located in the
		<filename>releases</filename> directory, the development version of
		the code is in the <filename>projects</filename> directory.
	</para>
</chapter>
