<chapter id="chapter-lib-install">
	<title>Setting up to use the Sesame libraries</title>
	<para>
		In this chapter, we explain some basics about setting up your
		application development environment to work with Sesame. In <xref
			linkend="chapter-repository-api"/> we go into details of the use
		of the APIs. If you do not want to program against the Sesame
		libraries but just want to install and run the Sesame HTTP server,
		please skip ahead to <xref linkend="chapter-server-install"/>.
	</para>

	<section> 
		<title>Downloading the libraries</title>
		<para>
			As was explained in <xref linkend="chapter-download"/>, various
			download options are available to you. The quickest way to get
			started with using the Sesame libraries is to download the Sesame
			<emphasis>onejar</emphasis> library and include it in your classpath. 	
		</para>
		<para>
			However, it is important to note that the Sesame Framework consists
			of a set of libraries: Sesame is not a monolithic piece of software,
			you can pick and choose which parts you want and which ones you
			don't. In those cases where you don't care about picking and
			choosing and just want to get on with it, the onejar is a good
			choice. If, however, you want a little more control over what is
			included, you can download the complete SDK and select (from the
			<filename>lib</filename> directory) those sesame libraries that you
			require.
		 </para>
	  </section>
	  <section>
		  <title>Using Apache Maven</title>
		<para>
			An alternative to picking libraries by hand is to use Maven. <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/">Apache Maven</ulink> is a software management tool that helps you by offering things like library version management and dependency management (which is very useful because it means that once you decide you need a particular Sesame library, Maven automatically downloads all the libraries that your library of choice requires in turn), and giving you a handy-dandy build environment. For details on how to start using Maven, we advise you to take a look at the Apache Maven website at <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/"/>. If you are familiar with Maven, here are a few pointers to help set up your maven project.
		 </para>
		 <section>
			<title>Maven Repository</title>
			<para>
			  OpenRDF Sesame has its own Maven repository. To configure your project to use the correct repository, add the following to your project's <filename>pom.xml</filename> (or to your Maven configuration file: <filename>settings.xml</filename>):
			<screen><![CDATA[
<repositories>
				 ...
		<repository>
			<id>aduna-opensource.releases</id>
			<name>Aduna Open Source - Maven releases</name>
			<url>http://repo.aduna-software.org/maven2/releases</url>
		</repository>
	</repositories>
]]></screen>
			</para>
		 </section>
		 <section>
			 <title>Maven Artifacts</title>
	    <para>
		The groupId for all Sesame core artifacts is
		<filename>org.openrdf.sesame</filename>.  For many projects you
		will need only a part of the Sesame framework. For example, if
		you require functionality for quick in-memory storage and
		querying of RDF, you will only need to include dependencies on
		the SAIL repository module (artifactId
		<filename>sesame-repository-sail</filename>) and the in-memory
		storage backend module (artifactId
		<filename>sesame-sail-memory</filename>).
	    </para>
	    <para>
		To include a maven dependency in your project that
		automatically gets you the entire Sesame core framework, use
		artifactId <filename>sesame-runtime</filename>. 
	 </para>
  </section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Logging: SLF4J initialization</title>
		<para>
			Before you begin using the Sesame libraries, one important
			configuration step needs to be taken: the initialization and
			configuration of a logging framework.
		</para>
		<para>
			Sesame uses the <ulink url="http://www.slf4j.org/">Simple Logging
				Facade for Java (SLF4J)</ulink>, which is a framework for
			abstracting from the actual logging implementation. SLF4J allows
			you, as a user of the Sesame framework, to plug in your own favorite
			logging implementation at deployment time. SLF4J supports the most
			popular logging implementations such as Java Logging, Apache Commons
			Logging, Logback, log4j, etc. See the SLF4J website for more info.
		</para>
		<para>
		  What you need to do is to determine/decide which
		  logging implementation you (are going to) use and
		  include the appropriate SLF4J logger adapter in your
		  classpath. For example, if you decide to use <ulink
			 url="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/">Apache
			 log4j</ulink>, you need to include the
		  SFL4J-Log4J adapter in your classpath. The SLF4J
		  release packages includes adapters for various logging
		  implementations; just download the SLF4J release
		  package and include the appropriate adapter in your
		  classpath (or, when using Maven, set the appropriate
		  dependency); <filename>slf4j-log4j12-(version).jar</filename>,
		  for example. 
		 </para>
		 <para>
			One thing to keep in mind when configuring logging is that SLF4J expects only a single logger implementation on the classpath. Thus, you should choose only a single logger. In addition, if parts of your code depend on projects that use other logging frameworks directly, you can include a <ulink url="http://www.slf4j.org/legacy.html">Legacy Bridge</ulink> which makes sure calls to the legacy logger get redirected to SLF4J (and from there on, to your logger of choice. When you set this up correctly, you can have a single logger configuration for your entire project.
		 </para>
	</section>
</chapter>
