<chapter id="chapter-server-install">
	<title>Server software installation</title>
	<para>
		In this section, we explain how you can install a Sesame HTTP 
		Server. You can skip this if you are not planning to run a Sesame
		server but intend to use Sesame as a library to program against.
	</para>

	<section id="section-server-required-software">
		<title>Required software</title>

		<para>
			The Sesame server software requires the following software:
		</para>

		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>Java 5 or newer</listitem>
			<listitem>
				A Java Servlet Container that supports Java Servlet API 2.4 and
				Java Server Pages (JSP) 2.0, or newer. We recommend using a
				recent, stable version of
				<ulink url="http://tomcat.apache.org/">Apache Tomcat</ulink>.
				At the time of writing, this is either version 5.5.x or 6.x.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>

	<section id="section-sesame-server-installation" xreflabel="Sesame server installation">
		<title>Sesame Server and Workbench installation</title>
		<para>
			The Sesame 2 server software comes in the form of two Java Web
			Applications: <emphasis>OpenRDF Sesame Server</emphasis> and
			<emphasis>OpenRDF Workbench</emphasis>.
		</para>
		<para>
			Sesame Server provides HTTP access to Sesame repositories and is
			meant to be accessed by other applications. Apart from some
			functionality to view the server's log messages, it doesn't provide
			any user oriented functionality. Instead, the user oriented
			functionality is part of OpenRDF Workbench. OpenRDF Workbench
			provides a web interface for querying, updating and exploring the
			repositories of a Sesame Server.
		</para>
		<para>
			If you have not done so already, you will first need to
			<ulink url="http://www.openrdf.org/download.jsp">download</ulink>
			the Sesame 2 SDK. Both Sesame Server and OpenRDF Workbench can be
			found in the <filename>war</filename> directory of the SDK. The
			war-files in this directory need to be deployed in a Java Servlet
			Container (see <xref linkend="section-server-required-software"/>).
			The deployment process is container-specific, please consult the
			documentation for your container on how to deploy a web application.
		</para>
		<para>
			After you have deployed the Sesame Server webapp, you should be able
			to access it, by default, at path <filename>/openrdf-sesame</filename>.
			You can point your browser at this location to verify that the
			deployment succeeded<footnote><para>There is a known issue (<ulink url="http://www.openrdf.org/issues/browse/SES-845">SES-845</ulink>) with deployment of the Sesame Server in <emphasis>Apache Tomcat version 7</emphasis>, where this link does not redirect to the correct location as expected. If you are running Sesameo on Tomcat 7, try accessing <filename>/openrdf-sesame/home/overview.view</filename> instead</para></footnote>. Your browser should show the Sesame welcome
			screen as well as some options to view the server logs, among other
			things. Similarly, after deployment, the OpenRDF Workbench should be
			available at path <filename>/openrdf-workbench</filename>.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Logging Configuration</title>
		<para>
			Both Sesame Server and OpenRDF Workbench use the
			<ulink url="http://logback.qos.ch/">Logback</ulink> logging framework.
			In its default configuration, all Sesame Server log messages are sent
			to the log file <filename>[ADUNA_DATA]/OpenRDF Sesame/logs/main.log</filename>
			(and log messages for the Workbench to the same file in
			<filename>[ADUNA_DATA]/OpenRDF workbench</filename>). See
			<xref linkend="chapter-datadir-config"/> for more info about data
			directories.
		</para>
		<para>
			The default log level is <parameter>INFO</parameter>, indicating that
			only important status messages, warnings and errors are logged.  The
			log level and -behaviour can be adjusted by modifying the
			<filename>[ADUNA_DATA]/OpenRDF Sesame/conf/logback.xml</filename>
			file. This file will be generated when the server is first run. Please
			consult the logback manual for configuration instructions.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Repository Configuration</title>
		<para>
			A clean installation of a Sesame Server has a single repository by
			default: the SYSTEM repository. This SYSTEM repository contains all
			configuration data for the server, including data on which other
			repositories exists and (in future releases) the access rights on
			these repositories. This SYSTEM repository <emphasis>should
					not</emphasis> be used to store data that is not related to
			the server configuration.
		</para>
		<para>
			The best way to create and manage repositories in a SYSTEM repository
			is to use the Sesame Console or OpenRDF Workbench. The Sesame Console
			is a command-line application for interacting with Sesame, see <xref
			  linkend="chapter-console"/>.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
