<chapter id="chapter-sesame2-whats-new">
	<title>Sesame 2: what's new?</title>
	<para>
		For those who have previously worked with Sesame 1.x:
		Sesame 2 is an important step forward from the Sesame 1.x
		series, building on the feedback that has been gathered
		during the past years. A lot of improvements have been
		made to various APIs as well as the framework as a whole.
	</para>
	<para>
		Unfortunately, because of all the changes to APIs and the
		like, Sesame 2 is not backwards compatible with earlier
		releases. Therefore, we suggest you read through this user
		guide before starting to port any applications to Sesame
		2. Please also note that Sesame 2 is currently in alpha
		stage, meaning that APIs can still change as a result of
		user feedback (and we suggest you use this opportunity!).
		It also means that many features are not yet implemented
		(for example, the Web interface and the RDBMS backend are
		not yet available).
	</para>
	<para>
		So what's new in Sesame 2? Well, in short:
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>Sesame 2 is completely targeted at Java 5. All APIs use
			Java 5 features such as typed collections.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>Revised Repository API that is much more targeted at
			embedded use of Sesame.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>Support for context/provenance, allowing you to keep track
			of individual RDF data units (like files, for instance).</listitem>

		<listitem>Proper transaction/rollback support</listitem>

		<listitem>A REST-ful HTTP protocol that includes support for the
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-protocol/">SPARQL
				protocol</ulink> and
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-XMLres/">SPARQL
				Query Results XML Format</ulink>, which are both Last Call
			Working Drafts from the W3C.</listitem>

		<listitem>Support for the
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/">SPARQL Query
				Language</ulink>, which was developed by Ryan Levering in a
			separate open source project:
			<ulink url="http://sparql.sourceforge.net/"/>.
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
		A lot of these new features will be covered in the next chapters.
	</para>
</chapter>
