<chapter id="chapter-sesame2-whats-new">
	<title>Sesame 2: what's new?</title>
	<para>
		For those who have previously worked with Sesame 1.x:
		Sesame 2 is an important step forward from the Sesame 1.x
		series, building on the feedback that has been gathered
		during the past years. A lot of improvements have been
		made to various APIs as well as the framework as a whole.
	</para>
	<para>
		Unfortunately, because of all the changes to APIs and the like,
		<emphasis>Sesame 2 is not backwards compatible with earlier
		  releases</emphasis>. Therefore, we suggest you read through this
		user guide before starting to port any applications to Sesame 2.
		Please also note that Sesame 2 is currently in beta stage, meaning
		that although the core APIs are now stable, many features are not
		yet implemented (for example, the custom inferencer and the RDBMS
		backend are not yet available).
	</para>
	<para>
		So what's new in Sesame 2? Well, in short:
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			Sesame 2 is completely targeted at Java 5. All APIs use
			Java 5 features such as typed collections and iterators.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			Revised Repository API that is much more targeted at
			the use of Sesame as a library.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			Support for context/provenance, allowing you to keep track
			of individual RDF data units (like files, for instance).
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			Proper transaction/rollback support.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			A REST-ful HTTP protocol that includes support for the
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-protocol/">SPARQL protocol</ulink> and
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-XMLres/">SPARQL Query Results XML Format</ulink>,
			which are currently both Last Call Working Drafts from the W3C.
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			Support for the
			<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/rdf-sparql-query/">SPARQL Query Language</ulink>.
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<para>
		A lot of these new features will be covered in the next chapters.
	</para>
</chapter>
